Guide to the Mexico Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Walter Howe, 1759-1821; Part II. II
  - Archivo General de la Nación
    - Cédulas Reales
      - Volume 167
        - Cédula No. 86. ["An order relative to the ad int. appointment of Conjueces de Alzadas. Crown orders that such appointments shall be made by President of the Court concerned, and not the Tribunal as it had urged; appointment to last until next meeting of Junta General."], 1797 (Box 63, Folder 141, Reel 23)
        - Cédula No. 170. ["Dispute between Audiencia and Deputation of Guadalajara. Case of usurpation of a mine belonging to a widow. Case had come before Audiencia before promulgation of Ordenanzas. Deputation claimed jurisdiction afterwards. Crown orders decision by court where case was begun - and that quickly."], 1797 (Box 63, Folder 141, Reel 23)
      - Volume 169. Cédula No. 126. ["An order approving a raise in pay for officials of Tribunal. Also urges zeal in administration of School of Mines, and orders some of best grads be chosen to go to Viceroyalty of Peru and B. A. as Managers and Engineers of Mines in order to improve methods there."], 1798 Apr 19 (Box 63, Folder 142, Reel 23)
      - Volume 171. Cédula No. 113. 1798 (Box 63, Folder 143, Reel 23)
      - Volume 174
        - Cédula No. 214. ["A dispatch accepting a donativo of 500,000 pesos from Tribunal de Minería and specifying that interest and principal shall be paid off by a tax of 3 gr. for every mark of silver refined - with Minería de Guanajuato excepted from this charge."], 1799 (Box 63, Folder 144, Reel 23)
        - Cédula No. 228. ["Discussion of desirability of creating two new Conjueces de Alzadas for Mexico City or whether Tribunal should settle all cases."], 1799 (Box 63, Folder 144, Reel 23)
      - Volume 175. Cédula No. 83. ["Answer to another objection of Tribunal's to outsiders entering into accounting of funds. Repeats former instructions (c.f. Vol. 137, #257) as to who shall check accounts and orders Viceroy to see that they are carried out."], 1800 Jun 24 (Box 63, Folder 145, Reel 23)
      - Volume 179
        - Cédula No. 38. ["Instructions regarding litigation involving the heirs of the Conde de Regla, Juzgado de Guadalajara...."], 1801 (Box 63, Folder 146, Reel 23)
        - Cédula No. 58. ["Instructions regarding the return of German experts to Mexico, salaries and expenses to be allowed them, etc."], 1801 (Box 63, Folder 146, Reel 23)
        - Cédula No. 59. ["An order lowering price of powder supplied to miners in return for the loan of 500,000 pesos granted by Tribunal # all in response to a request from Tribunal."], 1801 (Box 63, Folder 146, Reel 23)
        - Cédula No. 84. [ "A denuncio case involving the Deputation Territorial de Guanajuato, the Tribunal, and favoritism and corruption."], 1801 (Box 63, Folder 146, Reel 23)
      - Volume 186. Cédula No. 79. ["A Cédula regarding jurisdiction and settlement of a dispute over the inheritance of part of a mine in Catorce. Cédula is followed by a copy of the Tribunal's representation to the Crown in the matter."], 1802 (Box 63, Folder 147, Reel 23)
      - Volume 187
        - Cédula No. 40. ["Regarding the extinction of the Juzgado de Alzadas de Guadalajara and jurisdiction of Intendants, etc. of that jurisdiction in mining cases."], 1803 (Box 63, Folder 148, Reel 23)
        - Cédula No. 99. [ "A Royal Order about what shall be done in the case of endowed students in School of Mines who go AWOL. This is the case of Felipe Obregón who left to join the army."], 1803 (Box 63, Folder 148, Reel 23)
        - Cédula No. 122. ["Approval of the establishment of the Banco de Rescate de Platas in Guanajuato."], 1803 (Box 63, Folder 148, Reel 23)
        - Cédula Nos. 162 & 163. ["The grant of certain privileges in regard to Royal taxes and quicksilver to save mining industry from ruin."], 1803 (Box 63, Folder 148, Reel 23)
      - Volume 190
        - Cédula No. 71. ["A long Cédula about appeals in mining cases: # where final appeal lies, and procedure. Question arising out of an actual case; document sheds considerable light on legal aspects."], 1803 (Box 63, Folder 149, Reel 23)
        - Cédula No. 80. [ "A dispute about ownership of a mine in Catorce and right of a Swiss and a Presbyter to have interests in it."], 1803 (Box 63, Folder 149, Reel 23)
      - Volume 191
        - Cédula No. 45. ["Notice of invention of a new method of refining silver. Comments on apparent lack of interest of Tribunal. Orders inventor to appear before Elhuyar and explain invention, and if worth Tribunal is to lend aid in perfecting it."], 1804 (Box 63, Folder 150, Reel 23)
        - Cédula No. 47. ["Settlement of certain questions as to who might be elected Administrator General of Tribunal."], 1804 (Box 63, Folder 150, Reel 23)
      - Volume 198. Cédula No. 169. ["Concerning relations of Tribunal to Deputation of Guanajuato and payment of provincial Deputies. Approval of Viceroy's procedure."], 1807 Apr 30 (Box 63, Folder 151, Reel 23)
      - Volume 200. Cédula No. 47. ["Crown refuses to approve annulment of Tit. 16, Art. 1, of Ordenanzas."], 1808 Feb 29 (Box 63, Folder 152, Reel 23)
      - Volume 201. Cédula No. 230. ["An order regarding the distribution of quicksilver, in reply to a request from the Deputation of Guanajuato."], 1809 Sep 27 (Box 63, Folder 153, Reel 23)
      - Volume 206. Cédula No. 132. ["Approval of reestablishment of Bancos de Rescate in provincial mining centers # under certain restrictions and with care not to violate Title 10, Arts. 1 and 2 of Ordenanzas."], 1812 Feb 6 (Box 63, Folder 154, Reel 23)
      - Volume 208. Cédula No. 2. ["An important order replying to a complaint of Elhuyar's about the handling of the Fondo under the Administration of the Marques de San Juan de Rayas. Also some other points such as appointment of a new Asesor."], 1813 Feb 13 (Box 63, Folder 155, Reel 23)
      - Volume 211. Cédula No. 54. ["An important order caused by suggestions of ex#deputy of Zacatecas of Measures for bettering mining industry. Involves following points: (1) Extension of list of Articles exempt from Alcabala and circulation of this list to all Reales and Tax#collectors. (2) Distribution of quicksilver to be made by Tribunal and Provincial Deputations. (3) Tribunal to hold hearings and make recommendations as to advisability of annulling Tit. 3, Art. 5, of Ordenanzas. (4) Tribunal to give advice re. Tit. 3, Art. 4 # Jurisdiction etc. (5) Tribunal to give advice re. desirability of moving Tribunal de Alzadas of Guadalajara or establishing new ones in Zacatecas and Durango. (6) Tribunal to give advice re. usefulness of newly established Casa de Moneda of Zacatecas. (7) Tribunal to make general recommendations as to best way of restoring mining industry and repairing losses caused by Revolution."], 1814 Aug 8 (Box 63, Folder 156, Reel 23)
      - Volume 218. Cédula No. 324. ["A sequel to Vol. 211, No. 54 asking for recommendations as to what can be done to reform the Tribunal and resurrect the mining industry."], 1818 Jun 5 (Box 63, Folder 157, Reel 23)
      - Volume 221. Cédula No. 46. ["An order approving Viceroy's suspension of election of third Deputy General of Tribunal and reducing salary of Conjuez de Alzadas."], 1819 Jul 25 (Box 63, Folder 158, Reel 23)
      - Volume 225. Cédula No. 123. ["An important printed decree modifying radically the system of taxation of gold and silver. This is a decree passed by the Cortes of 1820 and makes very important concession to the mining industry."], 1821 Jul 15 (Box 63, Folder 159, Reel 23)
    - Minería
      - Volume 11. Reports on different mining districts. 1772-1774 (Box 63, Folder 160, Reel 23)
      - Volume 47
        - Nos. 5 and 6. Notes on miscellaneous correspondence. 1775-1776 (Box 63, Folder 161, Reel 23)
        - No. 9. [letter by the viceroy to tribunal de minería concerning the appointment of a mercury mine inspector.], 1781 Sep 19 (Box 63, Folder 162, Reel 23)
        - No. 10. [three letters written by the viceroy to the tribunal de minería, concerning the Real de los Catorce; royal gratitude for the tribunal's donativo to the Spanish crown; and measures to pay interest and sinking fund requirements on the donativo.], 1782 (Box 63, Folder 163, Reel 23)
      - Volume 48
        - No. 1. [letter from the tribunal de minería to the viceroy concerning discovery of copper and zinc mines. Letter from the viceroy to the tribunal concerning a junta general.], 1783 (Box 63, Folder 164, Reel 23)
        - No. 2. [dispatch concerning damage done by an earthquake in Guanajuato; letter from the viceroy to the tribunal de minería concerning a disputed election of deputies; and two dispatches by the royal auditor to the tribunal de minería, concerning the appointment of a juez de alzadas, and the tribunal's jurisdiction in mining cases.], 1784 (Box 63, Folder 165, Reel 23)
        - No. 3. [two dispatches from the royal auditor to the tribunal de minería, concerning a request by Guanajuato's miners for a salt monopoly and the payment of a debt to the tribunal de minería. Letter from the viceroy to the tribunal de minería concerning an impost on silver.], 1785 (Box 63, Folder 166, Reel 24)
        - No. 4. [three communications from the viceroy to the tribunal de minería concerning the tribunal's accounts; much delayed responses to previous communications from the tribunal; and the method to repay a 500,000 peso loan. Dispatch from the tribunal to the crown concerning the repayment of a loan.], 1786-1788 (Box 63, Folder 167, Reel 24)
        - No. 6. [communication from the royal auditor to the tribunal de minería seeking details concerning the tribunal's accounts. Three communications from the viceroy to the tribunal de minería concerning the tribunal's arreglo; excessive expenditures; and the avío accounts.], 1787 (Box 63, Folder 168, Reel 24)
        - No. 7. [document concerning excessive expenditures by the tribunal de minería; opinion by the fiscal concerning German miners; and two communications from the viceroy to the tribunal de minería concerning the junta general and Professor Rodríguez's salary.], 1788 (Box 63, Folder 169, Reel 24)
        - No. 8. [two dispatches from the viceroy to the tribunal de minería, concerning the lack of accomplishments of German miners, and the annulment of the election of Deputy Valcarce. List of expedientes pending before the tribunal de minería.], 1789 (Box 63, Folder 170, Reel 24)
        - No. 8a. [correspondence between the viceroy and tribunal de minería concerning problems due to a lack of mercury, and mining disasters in Guanajuato.], 1780 (Box 63, Folder 171, Reel 24)
        - No. 9. [two lists of expedientes pending before the tribunal de minería. Two letters from the viceroy to the tribunal de minería concerning a disputed election in the Real de los Catorce, and the tribunal's non-judicial jurisdiction. Communications concerning a jurisdictional dispute involving a provincial deputation. Text concerning the repayment of a loan.], 1790 (Box 63, Folder 172, Reel 24)
        - No. 10. [dispatch from the mining deputation of Bolaños to the tribunal de minería concerning the alcabala on mine supplies. Report on the weaknesses of Mexican mining industry.], 1782-1783 (Box 63, Folder 173, Reel 24)
      - Volume 49
        - No. 1. [two lists of expedientes pending before the tribunal de minería.], 1791 (Box 63, Folder 174, Reel 24)
        - No. 2. [list of expedientes pending before the tribunal de minería. Two different reports by Elhuyar concerning the School of Mines. Request by the tribunal de minería to the viceroy, concerning 100,000 pesos due from a loan.], 1792 (Box 63, Folder 175, Reel 24)
        - No. 3. [list of expedientes pending before the tribunal de minería. Report concerning the progress of the School of Mines.], 1793 (Box 63, Folder 176, Reel 24)
        - No. 4. [list of expedientes pending before the tribunal de minería.], 1794 (Box 64, Folder 177, Reel 24)
        - Nos. 7 and 9. [two texts concerning honors granted to Elhuyar, and a mine claim made by Valcarce.], 1797-1799 (Box 64, Folder 178, Reel 24)
      - Volume 63. [report to the viceroy on the present state of mines financed by the tribunal's bank; audit by Pedro María de Monterde of the general accounts presented by the tribunal de minería; list of the additional sums which the audit showed should be charged against the funds of the bank; and a series of notes and remarks on the tribunal's general accounts.], n.d. (Box 64, Folder 179, Reel 24)
      - Volume 95. [two expedientes concerning the tribunal de minería's exercise of jurisdicción contenciosa, and a petition by the tribunal de minería that the royal ordinances of 1793 be amended to eliminate the juzgado de alzadas of Guadalajara.], 1793-1800 (Box 64, Folder 180, Reel 24)
      - Volume 104. [three reports about the compañía general de mineros de Zacatecas concerning the company's formation, a meeting of the members of the company, and events that transpired after the meeting.], 1759-1765 (Box 64, Folder 181, Reel 24)
      - Volume 110. [handwritten notes and typescript translation of the secret vote of del Hierro.], n.d. (Box 64, Folder 182, Reel 24)
      - Volume 127. [handwritten notes and typescript concerning the election of the Zimapan mining deputation.], 1770 (Box 64, Folder 183, Reel 24)
      - Volume 155. [handwritten notes recording the opinions of three members of an unidentified committee.], ca. 1786 (Box 64, Folder 184, Reel 24)
      - Volume 156. [list of points that the members of the royal junta for the reorganization of the royal tribunal de minería to consider in their deliberations. Handwritten notes summarizing the positions of five committee members.], 1786 (Box 64, Folder 185, Reel 24)
      - Volume 200. [handwritten notes on three expedientes concerning a disagreement between the subdelegate of Taxco and the Taxco mining deputation; complaint by Pedro José de Verguesa about the delays with, and irregularities in, the tribunal de minería's procedures for hearing cases; a petition by the Guanajuato mining deputation concerning the real ordenanza of 1793.], 1793-1800 (Box 64, Folder 186, Reel 24)
      - Volume 208. [account of extraordinary expenses of the tribunal de minería from 1777-1787.], 1787 (Box 64, Folder 187, Reel 24)
      - Volume 214. [handwritten notes concerning alcabalas in various mining centers.], 1782 (Box 64, Folder 188, Reel 24)
    - Virreyes
      - 1a Series
        - Volume 5. No. 257. ["A letter about the failure of the company projected to foment mines in Provinces of Sonora and Sinaloa."], 1772 Mar 23 (Box 64, Folder 189, Reel 24)
        - Volume 6. No. 12. ["An informe about the state of the mining industry in Mexico, particularly in Pachuca & Rl. del Monte." Includes supporting materials from Minería branch Volume 148.], 1771 (Box 64, Folder 190, Reel 24)
        - Volume 15. Nos. 859 and 914. ["Two reports on the decline of the Tribunal General and Measures taken to rehabilitate it."], 1786 (Box 64, Folder 191, Reel 24)
        - Volume 26. No. 650. ["Letter enclosing two documents recording an acuerdo held to discuss changes in the jurisdiction of Tribunal and Audiencia in Mining cases - with viceroy's observations."], 1793 Sep 30 (Box 64, Folder 192, Reel 24)
        - Volume 30. Nos. 33 and 35. ["Two important dispatches about the Arreglo of the Tribunal and appointment of new officials."], 1791 Jan-Feb (Box 64, Folder 193, Reel 24)
        - Volume 37. No. 128. ["Important dispatch about the handling of the Fondo Dotal of the Tribunal and the rendering of Accounts."], 1799 Jun 26 (Box 64, Folder 194, Reel 24)
      - 2a Series
        - Volume 14. No. 883. ["Letter remitting a plan for forming a Company of Shareholders to work the mines of Sonora and Sinaloa."], 1771 Apr 27 (Box 64, Folder 195, Reel 24)
        - Volume 19. No. 130. Dispatch on the condition of the mines of Pachuca and Real del Monte. 1771 Dec 25 (Box 64, Folder 196, Reel 24)
        - Volume 22. No. 299. Dispatch on the condition of the mines of Pachuca and Real de Monte. 1772 Mar 25 (Box 64, Folder 197, Reel 24)
        - Volume 31. No. 614. ["Letter regarding the habilitation of the mines of Sonora...."], 1772 Oct 27 (Box 64, Folder 198, Reel 24)
        - Volume 48. No. 1290. ["Report of a Junta held to regulate the supply of Azogue - with the attendance of Diputados generales del Cuerpo de Minería."], 1774 Feb 24 (Box 64, Folder 199, Reel 24)
        - Volume 50. No. 4. ["Estado de las cantidades de plata y oro efectivamente a monedas en cada uno de los 41 años pasados desde principios de 1733 hasta el fin de 1773."], 1774 Mar 8 (Box 64, Folder 200, Reel 24)
        - Volume 54. Nos. 1396 and 1397. ["Reports on progress of Organization of Industry, and steps which should be taken...."], 1774 May 27 (Box 64, Folder 201, Reel 24)
        - Volume 58. No. 1534. ["Report on taxes on all gold and silver. Also señoreage as affecting the Fondo de Minería and letter accompanying the representacioón of 1774."], 1774 Sep 24 (Box 64, Folder 202, Reel 24)
        - Volume 59. Lassaga y Velázquez de León representation. 1774 (Box 64, Folder 203, Reel 24)
        - Volume 80. No. 2306. ["An important dispatch about Ordenanzas Cuerpo Azogues."], 1776 Jun 26 (Box 64, Folder 204, Reel 24)
        - Volume 87. No. 2730. ["An important dispatch relating to Señoreage and practices of the Cuerpo...."], 1777 Jan 27 (Box 64, Folder 205, Reel 24)
        - Volume 88. No. 2776. ["A dispatch reporting measures taken by the Viceroy to fulfill the Royal Order of 4 of October 1776 - Azogues and Organization of Cuerpo with accompanying document."], 1777 Feb 24 (Box 64, Folder 206, Reel 24)
        - Volume 94. No. 3164. ["A most important dispatch recounting the erection of the Tribunal etc. and with accompanying document recounting all the former Acta and election of officers."], 1777 Aug 27 (Box 64, Folder 207, Reel 24)
        - Volume 115. No. 4222. ["A letter with accompanying document regarding a request for certain privileges from the Deputación de Minería de Taxco and illustrative of some of the functions of a provincial deputation."], 1779 Jan 27 (Box 64, Folder 208, Reel 24)
        - Volume 131. No. 1760. ["A dispute over Azogues between the Tribunal and the Hacienda."], 1782 Aug 1 (Box 64, Folder 209, Reel 24)
        - Volume 136. No. 415. ["An important dispatch concerning a meeting of the Junta General de Minería and jurisdiction in the mining business."], 1785 Apr 26 (Box 64, Folder 210, Reel 24)
        - Volume 141
          - No. 38. Text on forced loans. 1787 (Box 64, Folder 211, Reel 24)
          - No. 202. ["Dispatch giving information about the destruction by fire of the five principal mines of Real de Bolaños, and the action of the local deputations."], 1787 (Box 64, Folder 211, Reel 24)
        - Volume 148. No. 667. ["A dispatch concerning measures taken in regard to the German Miners and Professors arrival to enter the Royal Service."], 1788 Nov 27 (Box 64, Folder 212, Reel 24)
        - Volume 149. No. 124. ["A dispatch giving accounts of the jurisdiction of the Tribunal de Minería, and the expenses of a new jail."], 1788 Sep 25 (Box 64, Folder 213, Reel 24)
        - Volume 153. No. 124. ["An important order censuring Viceroy for allowing Audiencia to take jurisdiction in a mining case involving mines of La Serena, Guanajuato, Carmago. In spite of care Audiencia's decision, it is ordered nullified and case returned to proper jurisdiction under Ordenanzas."], 1792 Nov 8 (Box 64, Folder 214, Reel 24)
        - Volume 158. No. 82. Dispatch about the German miners, their activities and the actions of the viceroy. 1790 Sep 26 (Box 64, Folder 215, Reel 24)
        - Volume 162
          - No. 596. ["A dispatch concerning a denuncio of a mine and the action taken by the Tribunal."], 1791 (Box 64, Folder 216, Reel 24)
          - No. 669. ["A very important dispatch about the establishment of the School of Mines."], 1791 (Box 64, Folder 216, Reel 24)
        - Volume 165. Nos. 59 and 116. ["Two dispatches concerning the jurisdiction of the provincial disputations de Minería - Guanajuato."], 1792 May-Jun (Box 64, Folder 217, Reel 24)
        - Volume 166. No. 232. ["A dispatch concerning the denuncio de la Minería, action of the Tribunal and chief deputations." Also included are two summaries of other texts in this volume.], 1792 (Box 64, Folder 218, Reel 24)
        - Volume 168
          - No. 403. ["A letter about the building site for the School of Mines and the measures taken by the Tribunal."], 1792 (Box 64, Folder 219, Reel 24)
          - No. 429. A text concerning the Serena mines of Guanajuato. 1792 (Box 64, Folder 219, Reel 24)
        - Volume 169. No. 508. ["Dispatch reporting on the Arreglo of the Tribunal and its new Functions."], 1793 May 29 (Box 64, Folder 220, Reel 24)
        - Volume 170
          - No. 616. ["An important dispatch about the Donativo and financial affairs of the Tribunal and of Guanajuato."], 1793 (Box 64, Folder 221, Reel 24)
          - No. 713. [A text concerning German mining teachers.], 1793 (Box 64, Folder 221, Reel 24)
        - Volume 174. No. 966. ["An important dispatch re. the annulment of Article 1 Title 16 of Ordenanzas and contributions by the miners to the Fondo Dotal."], 1794 May 31 (Box 64, Folder 222, Reel 24)
        - Volume 180
          - No. 243. ["Dispatch illustration method followed in elections by the Tribunal General."], 1795 (Box 64, Folder 223, Reel 24)
          - No. 278. ["A report on the development of mines in Guatemala."], 1795 (Box 64, Folder 223, Reel 24)
        - Volume 183. No. 590. ["Dispatch concerning the Royal disapproval of certain acts of the deputation of Temascaltepec."], 1796 Feb 26 (Box 64, Folder 224, Reel 24)
        - Volume 192
          - No. 53. ["Interesting Dispatch about the supply of quicksilver and state of the Mining Industry."], 1798 (Box 64, Folder 225, Reel 24)
          - Nos. 116, 162, 164. [ "....dispatches dealing with the Donativo made to the Crown by the Tribunal and recommendations that Elhuyar's pay be increased for his part in bringing this about and other better reasons."], 1798 (Box 64, Folder 225, Reel 24)
        - Volume 199
          - No. 762. ["This dispatch is an account of the election of officers by the Tribunal and certain questions arising therefrom."], 1800 (Box 64, Folder 226, Reel 24)
          - No. 782. ["A long letter about the German mining experts, the expiration of the term of their contract and what should be done with them in the future."], 1800 (Box 64, Folder 226, Reel 24)
        - Volume 202. No. 122. ["Dispatch concerning the Juzgado de Alzadas of Guadalajara and certain representations of the Tribunal."], 1800 Sep 26 (Box 64, Folder 227, Reel 24)
        - Volume 208. No. 600. Text concerning German mining experts. 1802 May 27 (Box 64, Folder 228, Reel 24)
        - Volume 213. No. 152. ["Dispatch concerning privileges granted to some mines at Real del Monte a company of stockholders to run them."], 1803 Jun 26 (Box 64, Folder 229, Reel 24)
        - Volume 214. No. 305. ["Dispatch discussing the state of mining industry with reference to the quicksilver situation."], 1803 Oct 27 (Box 64, Folder 230, Reel 24)
        - Volume 219. No. 578. ["Some question in regard to one of the German miners."], 1804 Aug 27 (Box 64, Folder 231, Reel 24)
        - Volume 224. No. 814. ["A report on the scale of wages fixed by the Tribunal for mining engineers."], 1805 Jun 27 (Box 64, Folder 232, Reel 24)
        - Volume 229. No. 1041. ["Important letter about certain relations between the Tribunal and the Deputation de Guanajuato referring to articles 15 & 36 of the Ordenanzas."], 1806 Aug 27 (Box 64, Folder 233, Reel 24)
        - Volume 239